[music]
Tell me.
Hey. Hey. Hey.
[music]
Hi everybody. Today is Wednesday, June
3rd. This is Daniel Bush with POV Pool.
In every sport, at every level, a
competitor who's looking to improve his
or her skill should look at mental
focus. Uh, does the mental focus
separate the shortstop from the
professional pool player? When a
competitor has all the fundamentals,
knowledge, and skill, what will separate
him or her from being a top level
player? The mental game of pool is not
something that people focus on a lot,
but in truth, they should. Today on POV
Pool, we have one of the world's best
competitors
uh with us and top players in the game
coming to us originally from the
Netherlands, Neils, the Terminator Fen.
Welcome, Neils. It's a pleasure to have
you on the show today.
Thank you, Daniel. Appreciate it.
[snorts]
Um Neils, you've won numer numerous
championships, accolades. You've had
recognition for over 20 years now in the
game of pool. Fourtime, is it four-time
MVP for team Europe on the Musone Cup? I
think.
Yeah, correct. I'm getting a little old.
[laughter]
Well,
we're all standing in the same line, I
think. You know, [laughter]
uh you uh are a two-time world champion.
Um, you've gotten medal after medal on
the Euro tour in uh in Europe and uh you
know your resume just goes on and on.
All that being said, you're probably one
of the best qualified people in the
world to discuss what it takes to be a
professional pool player.
So, let's talk about Terminator College.
You just started started this up.
Well, yeah. Like Daniel, like you say, I
had the idea in the pool world for many
years. I was looking around, of course,
and I I've been a competitor for for
more than 20 years, and uh what I always
found fascinating about the sport is
when you asked people how big the mental
side of the game is, everybody would
say, "Oh, it's 80%, it's 90%, it's so
big." And I was looking around myself
for years and I saw hardly anybody do
anything with this train this right and
it was even like it was it was almost
like you were foolish if you were doing
it or you uh or you were kind of like
weak right that's the biggest thing
nowadays if you if you're
if you are talking about stuff mentally
that are not working well then you show
weakness and for guys that's a really
big thing
and [clears throat] and then I started
realizing, you know what, I just think
like people are [snorts] not aware of
where to start with their mental game.
They don't have the tools. They don't
have any clue really what they should
work on, how much they should work on
it. And I got this idea so for a few
years, but of course I I was always
touring. I was on the road competing, so
I didn't have much time to really work
it out. And I didn't really know what to
do with this. And then uh I went on
holiday to Egypt in January and I was
just I was just ready for it. It was
amazing. I just had this thing come over
me and I said, you know what? I want to
do an online course. I think now is a
great time with all the media
possibilities, the online course
platforms.
And I think with with 20 to 25 years of
experience [snorts] and working with
professional uh sports psychologists,
reading a ton of books, personal
development classes, I said I have a lot
of information that I can share with
pool players to help them out and give
them an arsenal to develop their mental
skills. And that's how it really
started. Mhm. How did you like when did
you
kind of realize that this was a mental
uh uh process? Because I know you know
you you've been a professional for over
20 years now. Was it before that time
you became a professional that you you
you know you or have you know were
overcoming the mental side of it or was
this still a process that you've been
going through in the past 20 years? Um,
well, I was always interested in the
mental side of the sport. I remember
when I was about 19 years old. I was I
just I I remember I think I had a couple
of problems with my mental game early on
and excuse me, I went to the library and
looked up some some things about the
mental side of the game and there was
one book that was called um I think it
was mental support for for athletes or
something like this in English.
And I read the book and it was I thought
it was pretty interesting. That was just
the first book I read about the mental
side of of sport.
And uh of course the older I got, the
more I traveled, the more books I
bought, the more things I worked with,
got help with, the more arsenal I
gathered myself.
Um so yeah, it it just made me more
complete in in experience, knowledge,
and what I could share with with other
pool players.
Did you uh you know one one of the
realizations for me when I was a pool
player was I noticed it was an attention
span. My attention
to the table was uh was something that
was weak and I had to work on that. So
you know just simply looking at the you
know contact points of the balls became
difficult for me sometimes.
and uh you know
do you address stuff like that? Do you
address things like anger?
Yeah, I I I think the uh attention span
nowadays is a very important thing
because people they get more and more
distracted during the day in general.
That's just the way that our society
works now with the with the cell phones
and all
the technology. And I think you have to
make choices. If you are wanting to get
much better at a at a sport that demands
extremely high concentration,
you have to work on your focus. And the
more distractions you have, the less
focus you have. That's just how it
works. So if you can start cutting out
some of your distractions, your focus
will automatically improve. So that of
course we're we're looking at focus and
like you say, anger, right? That's a
part of the uh
that's a blocker.
Sorry,
it's a blocker.
Anger anger is is a form of a part of
tilt, right? It's uh anger, frustration,
and that leads to bad play. And that's
that's tilt. So, in mental match play,
the third chapter, we go over a bunch of
really cool examples. uh mistake tilt,
opponent tilt, equipment tilt,
entitlement tilt, where you feel like
you should beat this guy every time and
and boom, your focus goes down. So
really cool stuff that I also have been
uh experiencing over the years and that
I've learned to work with.
So there's there's a ton of stuff in
there for all levels, right, from
beginners to top professionals.
Um so it's a really complete package.
I've really dug deep and got the most
out of it. It's 33 videos and slides,
workbook, and then at the end, you get
30 minutes of Skype with me oneon-one to
go over uh things that you could use
some steering with yourself.
Yeah.
Well, that's great. Did Did you notice
there was a void in the industry for
this type of uh education?
Yeah, I felt uh there's a ton of really
really good instructional stuff out
there on the table.
So, we're talking like Darren Appleton's
videos, the Billyard brothers with Fedor
and Maxim and those boys, you know, they
they pump out drills left and right.
Torsson's doing a great job.
So, there is plenty out there to work on
your game, but there is zero out there
to work on your mental game. And I
thought like like I said, I was just
astonished for years like
there's nothing out there and it's and
the mental side is so big. So what's
going on here? You know, it's like I
want to do this. I wanna I wanna
I want to give a package to the players
uh that they can work with. And uh yeah,
I I I feel like right now was really the
time. At first I thought I have to
really hurry this up. But then when I
was into the process of making it, I
said, you know what? I think I can I can
slow down a little bit because nobody's
going to do this for a while, like this
big of a course because it took so much
effort to make this thing with all the
videos,
the workbooks, and it's still not done.
I'm still working like on Japanese
translations. I'm working together with
Kamui now. really excited to bring out
the whole uh website fully in Japanese
for the market over there. That's going
to be uh in the upcoming weeks.
Oh wow. Okay. Because I know
Yeah, because you have you have this
already translated in Spanish,
uh chi is it Chinese, Mandarin or which
languages do you have this already?
Yeah, it's uh the subtitles are in
Spanish. Then we have German and we have
Chinese.
German and and Okay. And I'm working on
Italian also.
Oh, great.
I'm working on Japanese right now. So,
not I'm not sitting still, but
[laughter]
Well, good. Good. Uh, did So, it's it's
a it's quite an extensive course. You
you know, you just discussed that you
got six sections, lots of videos, a
workbook as well. Sounds like you know,
you've you've been you've covered all
the bases here and a Skype call. So,
have you have you done any Skype calls
yet? H how has that, you know,
experience been for you doing the Skype
meetings with students?
Yeah, yesterday I had a Skype meeting
with Mark Morris from the UK and it was
it was really cool. He had uh some
really nice questions
and he actually came uh up with a form
of tilt that I wasn't really aware of.
He was explaining I think he doesn't
mind if I tell this. He was explaining a
situation where he was playing a player.
Mhm.
Who was really nagging about the roles.
So when Mark was getting some rolls, he
would really rub it in and he was
getting frustrated by this. And then
midway the match, you could see the
rolls started to turn. So this opponent
start getting rolls and now it was like
he was getting quiet and Mark of course
was thinking, "Oh, now you're happy."
like you know so it's a form of tilt
where you're frustrated about the guy's
attitude and it's distracting you in
your mind and I thought this was really
fascinating so we spoke about that and I
was I was helping him with that but it
was kind of a new form of tilt and
that's also in the workbook you can
write down your own uh experiences that
you that you go through so I thought
that was really cool and we spoke about
uh that he started meditating that was
really working great for him he said,
and also in the corona time now, he said
the first weeks of being home, he was
bouncing off the walls because he was
just there in the house, right, in
quarantine with his thoughts. And he
said
the course really forced him to kind of
work on himself and and to start
implementing some new techniques. And he
said it was the one of the best things
he's done because he's he's more relaxed
and uh it's really helping him. So yeah,
that's that's really positive uh
feedback. It's great.
Yeah. Uh you know,
playing pool is is a is a very
fascinating sport because I mean it's
you know it is there is a a mental
aspect to it that's really really
important. It's paramount, you know. Um,
but uh, one thing that I found
interesting is that your opponent can
also push you mentally off your path.
You know what I'm saying?
But also on the right path.
Uh, in what sense? Give you you mean
motivate you?
Yeah. I mean, uh, if we talk about
motivation, the ideal situation is that
all your motivation comes from inside.
It's intrinsic motivation,
right? And uh that means that you're
firing yourself up because of your
goals. The goal setting free course that
I have that goes uh talks about that.
Yeah.
But of course if you look at uh attitude
a part of the course it's a great topic
attitude. I love this section. It's like
16 minutes long and I go all over all
kind of attitude facets. And one of the
things is also opponents. the way you
look at your opponents and
instead of being afraid like oh god I
got to play this guy right it's like
if there's a great player you have to
realize that that player is going to
force you to focus you have to focus
100% right
and he's going to push you to your
highest level like when I was a
youngster and I was playing effort or
boosty I knew like these guys are going
to pound me if I'm not on my game so it
made me really focus hard right already
an hour, two hours before the match, I
would really get him ready for it. So
like
you shouldn't be dependent on your
opponent to do this, but if you have a
really strong guy facing you or lady,
right,
it can help you to bring out the best in
your abilities. That's what I mean by
that.
Yeah.
Well, that's great. uh you know I I can
imagine people h how has the course uh
been going so far since you launched the
site the by the way the site again is uh
terminator-col.com
and uh it's the mental edge for
competitive pool players and how to
break your
through your inner roadblocks and unlock
unlock your true full pot and full
potential. Um and when did you launch
this? You launched this just less than
two weeks ago, right?
I think it's been three weeks now.
Oh, three weeks.
Was it the 12th?
Good.
I think
Yeah, I think it was the 12th of uh May.
Th Thursday, I think it was the 12th.
Yes.
Yeah. Uh yeah, things have been going
great. I've had a lot of contact with
people uh who were asking a lot of
questions. We had some some really good
sales, some really great feedback from
all kinds of countries. There's been
sales in from a lot of different country
countries also Qatar, USA, Germany. Uh,
a lot of variety. So, it's it's been
really exciting. And like I said, I'm
not sitting still. I'm keeping
I keep thinking about how I can improve
things and add things like the subtitles
now. Uh so it's still work in progress
in in the sense that it's it's going to
grow and and expand and it's not just
one static thing for the next 10 years.
But
still having said that the product is
out there and that's the great thing,
you know, there's like a big mental tool
out there for for pool players that want
to get better,
right?
And it's there for for the taking. So
that if they want to get stronger in
their minds, then you know it's there
forever. So it's great.
How about how about some of your
students? Have they been uh peers of
yours? Like you know, some of them you
already know that you you know have
potential.
Uh yeah, we of course Fedor Fedor joined
the course pretty fast.
Fedor.
Yeah, of course. I've known him of
course since he was a kid. Yeah,
extremely talented player.
Well, you know, talent or skilled,
that's also the debate, right? I I
always refer to skill because that kid
works really really hard.
And uh talent is in my opinion very
overrated because you see Joshua, Jason,
Fedor, you can name all these. Oh, they
got so much talent. But if you look at
the quality hours that they pump into
their training, it's it's not as much
talent. They really work on their game,
right?
Okay.
So, it's just what you put into it is
what you get out of it. And that's they
are really good examples.
Um,
what was I saying? Um, oh yeah, and then
we had uh also a lady player from
Germany, Ena Coplan. She joined, really
good player. We had another German
player, Christov Ranches. I've had many
battles with him in the German league.
Really, really strong player. Also one
of the best straight pool players in
Germany. He joined up. Then we had uh
from Qatar Muhammad uh I'm missing his
last name, but I've played him in the
China Open. I remember last 64.
Okay.
And we also had from Kuwait, uh,
Ber B,
what's his last name? You catching me
off Carter B. [snorts] I played him last
64 in the world championships last year.
Okay.
Not the last edition, but the year
before we played last 64. So very, very
strong players. Like they played major
tournaments like last 64, last 32.
Well, that that has to feel good, you
know. It has to be a good indication to
you that um that the course that you're
presenting is uh is on a solid
foundation, right?
Yeah, it's it's great. But I' I was
pretty confident about that because the
stuff I'm putting in there is for, like
I said, for any level,
but it's also stuff that I've worked
with myself. So, it's not just, oh,
here's a book, let's put this in and
let's put this. I've been through the
entire process of this course. the
highs, but also the very very lows. I
talk about open wounds,
uh, shame and projection, things that
people do not want to talk about. But
when you're playing Moscone Cup and and
things are not working for you, you want
to crawl under the table. You want to
get out of there. You're embarrassed,
ashamed,
uh, you're wounded, right? So, it's
these things I also discuss from
personal experience. And then of course
the heist. When you win MVPs, world
titles, you know, if you're if you're uh
becoming a top pool player, you're going
to experience everything, right? You're
going to fall on your butt. You're going
to stand on the top of the stage. It's
all going to be there. It's not one not
[clears throat] one easy ride to the
top.
But that's that makes it an adventure,
right?
And yeah. And that for me is actually
the reason why I'm still playing because
every time I get to that airport, not
now, but every time I step foot on in
the airport, I have no clue what's going
to happen. I could I could win the whole
thing or I could win maybe one match and
go out, but I try to have a great trip
anyway. And uh I just love that
adventure about the game. So uh
that's awesome.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So, like last week, I think um
uh Kamui, one of your sponsors, they
released a video with you, uh doing
commentary describing
the mental journey you had through a
match with Dennis Oro
at the Worldpool Masters in 2018. I must
say it was pretty indepth analysis of uh
what you as a professional goes through
in a match. Has uh has going through
postgame analysis always been a part of
your game?
Uh yes, postgame analysis. Yes, it has
been some on some occasions not as
thorough as it could have been because
back then maybe I didn't have the tools.
But if I'm uh if I'm serious about my
game, uh the feedback loops that I have,
excuse me, that I work in uh within the
course,
postmatch uh the postmatch stuff. That's
great because what it does for you is
you can just write down the steps like
okay well how was my preparation my
result uh my analysis and uh bring it
back to the the next practice session
for the next event right so you create
this loop
10 15 minutes and you go you can go on
with the rest of your day instead of
sitting in that in that hotel room like
this
brooding
oh what have I done idiot
Right? And then you have actually a
lousy day and you're actually really
hurting yourself because it's a lot of
negative talk.
Uh and you could go into like a dip
instead of
instead of realizing like, hey, what
were the things that actually went
really well? Hey, I was breaking really
well. I was jumping really well.
Yeah, I just missed that ball 77. That
was pretty easy. But
you know what I mean? So maybe you
weren't even playing bad. you were
playing really good, but you made one
critical error, but that doesn't mean
you're you're out of stroke or whatever.
So, it gives you a lot of insight
in
um analyzing your stuff more like an
athlete and not like somebody who
doesn't know what he's doing,
right? You [snorts] have to be uh
somewhat detached from your own
performance in a in a way.
Yeah, that's a good way to put it. And
that helps you if you see that stuff in
front of you, it helps you to be more
objective to what actually went on
instead of only emotional about what
went on.
Yeah. Yeah.
So, of course, if you lose a match,
you're not going to be happy. But it
could very well be that you just played
a good match and things just
right, they got out of control. And
that's that's also the nature of
nineball. The most tournaments we play
are nineball tournaments. There is just
this 10 15 uh percent of luck variance
in the game.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right. You can you can break great park
the cube on the middle of the table and
get kicked in the corner.
Stuff like that. It just or the guy
misses a ball and you're stuck behind
things that are just out of your hands.
So
you have to keep playing the game the
right way and the variance will
eventually turn back to even the more
tournaments and matches you play.
Well, that's the reality of the game,
isn't it? You're going to [snorts] have
you're going to have those bad moments
and and uh probably one of the toughest
uh uh obstacles mentally is to not is to
you know is the difficulty in letting
those moments go and knowing being able
to recognize those moments as something
that's out of your control. You know,
you can't you can't always control the
outcome of how the ball breaks. You know
what I mean? [laughter]
No. And also for for mistakes, I
remember
uh the year I won the world title
2014. I was working really hard on my
mental game and my tactical game all in
the same year.
And things were really coming together
in during the the World Championships.
And it wasn't because I was playing
flawless,
but it was it was because if I made an
error, I was able my mental I was
mentally so fit, I could put it aside
immediately and bounce back twice as
hard. If I made an error, boom, next
rack, breaker, run out, right? I was
like stepping it up instead of letting
it affect me. And that's if you do a lot
of mental positive work,
that's the reward you're going to get.
you get so strong with your awareness,
how your own mental traps work,
uh, and you can catch yourself much
quicker uh, when you get mentally a
little weak and you can adapt much
faster.
So, right now, what's I mean, we we're
kind of in quarantine here in the United
States. I don't know what the situ
You're in Denmark right now, is that
correct?
Right. Right.
Don't know what the situation is there.
you know, you feel free to elaborate on
that, but um what's taking up more time
for you uh lately? Um are you is it uh
are you are you practicing? Are you
getting back into the game at all? Are
you I know that you're you're working uh
to compete on a on a small level, right,
with uh some online tournaments, but uh
is this course taking up a lot of your
time? Have you had time for family?
What's uh what's a typical day for you
now?
Well, when I came back from Vegas, uh
like you said, we also went into
quarantine, and that's over 10 weeks
ago.
Yeah.
Um I had to do a lot of work with the
kids. It was a lot of homeschool things
going on. So, in the mornings, I was
working with the oldest, Lena, and uh
like for over two hours doing school
work. Mhm.
Then in the afternoons we would uh go on
trips, you know, keep the kids involved,
entertained. Uh we could still go
outside because if you're stuck in the
house that that wouldn't improve
anything. We were still allowed to go
into nature. So we did a lot of walks
and things like that. And then gradually
I had more time to work on the project,
the course. I said, you know what? I'm
really gonna hammer this project now
because I have time. So, I want to put
in at least two, three hours a day of
filming, editing, working on the
workbook, the quick learn guides, uh,
computer stuff. So, I really started
dedicating myself to that part. And that
just meant that my pool game I just set
aside for a moment because
there was no light at the end of the
tunnel for when we were going to
compete.
Yeah.
So, I was really in good stroke when I
was in Vegas. And so it was a downer
that I had to go home.
Yeah. You had to you had to actually
drop out of the world uh the world
predator event, didn't you?
I chose to leave the um the first event,
the uh Predator.
I mean, they canled it anyway, but you
you left early anyways, didn't you?
No, they canceled the second event.
Okay.
And I left I left the first event
because
Right.
the news went so quick and things
escalated. so fast
that uh my airline company wrote out a u
news message that they were not going to
fly out of the USA during the lockdown
the the announced lockdown from Trump
and that kind of went into a process of
like okay what's what's really happening
here and we were talking with the
federation I was talking with uh my dad
who called me in the middle of the night
and he doesn't call me for no
uh like major decisions in my life. I've
dealt with him like selling my house,
things like that. So when he called me
up, I was like this this is really
serious stuff. I have to make a decision
here. And
we spoke with various people for two,
three hours in the middle of the night
till 3:00 in the morning. And I decided
like uh I could get stuck here for a
couple of months and I have I have young
kids back home and and my wife and I
said I'm I'm I'm not taking a chance.
I'm going back home.
Yeah.
And things escalated in Vegas and they
uh they canled event number two which I
thought was a good move personally.
But here in Denmark actually things have
been opening up more and more. They were
really fast with locking things down.
So they had things under control pretty
quick. And the positive thing about
Denmark is that pretty much all the
countryside is very spread out. So you
have Copenhagen with over a million
people. That's where a lot of corona
cases were. But then
the rest of the country have like
villages and small towns. So the
infection rate wasn't that critical and
it was under control quick. So the
schools have been open now for four
weeks. Great.
And uh yeah, people have been allowed to
gather up now with over 10 20 people.
Okay.
So, so I've been cycling with the local
club with with over 10 people. Stuff
like that, you know. It's still you can
have some social activities.
Yeah. And the Yeah, the game uh I've
been competing in the uh the WSA arena,
the online event they've been holding.
I'm I'm trying to get back a stroke
through that because I got to play the
15 ball ghost with which is brutal. So,
uh
Well, where where you where are you
ranking right now within that
competition?
I I won my first two matches and then I
lost the third uh and I've played my
fourth match this morning. So, that was
in the last 25 of the loser side, I
think.
Right.
And I'm still waiting if that was good
enough. I ran six racks out of 15, which
which is decent. Um,
playing 15 ball.
Playing 15. If I'm running six, seven,
or eight racks, I'm happy. I mean,
yeah, [laughter]
it's tough. It's super tough because if
you break and you get clusters and
sometimes you can't even open them up
after the break, so
Right.
It's hard. So, but that's good. Uh, it's
good [laughter] to get the competitive
juices out.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, you're not you're
not beating the ghost, but six out of 15
is
it's pretty amazing. That's amazing.
Yeah. I wonder because they said
somewhere that Jason uh Jason Shaw has
the hot seat. I don't really know how
that works, but he must have he must
have won a tournament with the 15 ball
ghost or something. I'm I'm not sure.
Wow. Wow.
That that's got to be really different
though. uh or or maybe not Neil Neils
the mental aspect of your game when
you're just playing the ghost versus
playing a real life opponent. What's is
there a comparison there? Have you been
noticing it?
Oh yeah. I've I've been struggling with
those uh things. I get really confronted
with my focus also because I haven't
been playing that much. So my my
daydream moments are way more intense.
And of course, you're not playing in a
in a a tournament setup where there's
tourn tables here, tables there, and you
have that
tournament vibe. You're just uh in your
own comfort room,
right? There's no there's no crowd to
feed off of either.
No. No. So, the the the vibe is a little
bit different. So, you really have to
prepare well. I know match three I had
to do some computer work in the morning
and I it was taking up some time and
then I had to do the challenge because I
ran into time problems and my focus was
just not there.
I see.
So this morning I said listen I want to
get a good session in. I'm going to go
meditate in the morning uh get ready and
then um I want to do my inning and it my
focus was much better. So
is there any is there visualization that
you go through too?
uh I have done uh many visualizations.
Yeah, that's part of the course. I uh
there's a great uh great book which I'm
not going to tell but that uh I deal
with a lot of great uh exercises from
that and I know Phil Jackson from the
Chicago Bulls [snorts] which is nice now
with the last dance documentary. He has
lo he has used
uh stuff from that book to work with the
Chicago Bulls players. Mhm.
Very powerful uh visualization tools,
the bottles exercise.
U
check out the course. [laughter]
Okay. Yeah, definitely. Uh once again,
that's the um
uh that is the uh terminator-col.com.
Uh I really like your I love that image
of you sitting on the eightball uh uh on
the water there.
What? What beach is that?
It's not me. [laughter]
Oh, that's not you.
Okay,
that's funny.
We spoiled it. No, my um
And those aren't And those aren't real
balls in the water either.
No, no, my step my stepdad. It's at
least the husband of my the second
husband of my mother stepdad.
Okay.
Uh he is a graphical designer and he uh
he um put the balls in there. I saw the
stones and I had this idea. I said,
"Man, if we make pool balls out of those
stones, this is like a great picture for
the for the for the front of the
course." So,
it's always um
it's a the creative process of uh of
enterprise like this is is is always
exciting, isn't it?
Yeah.
Yeah,
it is good.
You have to find
pictures. You have to you have to learn
how to videotape yourself. You have to
work on the lighting, on the sound, on
slideshows,
all this kind of stuff. The the software
for the online platform,
etc., etc. So,
it's a big learning big learning curve
for you. Not just that's not just the
mental part, that's just uh you know
technical knowledge.
Yeah. All technical knowledge. Yeah.
It's very exciting.
Yeah. uh but also frustrating because uh
sometimes you just don't know how things
work in the software and you have to
send a mail to the support desk, you
have to wait a few days, you have to dig
on YouTube like how does this work, you
know? Uh
tell me about it.
Yeah, it's it's amazing. It's like
Well, if you take if you take YouTube
for example, they change their platform
like every couple of months. You're
like, "Yeah, wait a minute. I was just
doing it the certain way for for the
last couple of months. Now I got to
change my whole procedure." You know,
that's
Yeah. The same for Facebook actually
because the
Facebook too. Yeah.
The Facebook live now with the with the
whole new live producer and then the
camera doesn't work on this uh on this
thing. You have to go back to the old
thing. So, it's all these technical
right
details and I'm I'm investing now in
getting new camera set up for the for
the table here at home because the
quality is really low.
So, I bought new camera, bought new
wifi, bought new uh routers. So, I got
to get all that stuff uh up and running
in the next week and then the quality is
going to be much better.
Well, that's great. Um, and speaking of
which, for the uh for the viewer out
there who wants to follow you, who wants
to watch you uh streaming from your home
studio or uh any of the uh events that
you're competing in that are online? Uh
is there any way that we can follow you
besides uh just Facebook or is there a
YouTube channel? There's no YouTube
channel uh as yet but uh I might start
implementing that uh depending on what's
going to work better. I think I will
start with Facebook live in the
beginning but YouTube's also a good way
to to link the both both of those
platforms together.
Okay. But I think what I'm what I want
to support and bring more forward is
that
people nowadays, they're really addicted
to the highlights. They want to see that
that one run out of a drill, but that's
not really the reality of the world.
[laughter]
And it's not really the reality of how a
professional gets to the level of
running out that drill. Yeah.
What's also interesting is that he has
to put in the hours
of deliberate practice before he he can
run that rack. So I'm what I want to do
is just show uh the training session
and not one great shot that I made in
the training session because I feel it's
not a thing. It's great. It's
entertaining, but it's it's also
something that's a little bit uh taking
away from reality and people I I feel
it's a little bit dangerous because
people nowadays think that everybody
everything should go easy and fast
and that's just not how it is. You have
to put the time in.
Kind of reminds me of that um
that Chris Meling run out from the world
the
MA.
Yeah. against Ma where like every shot
was like incredibly difficult and lucky
as well if you think about it. I mean he
he he's an amazing player, don't get me
wrong. But for him to be able to do that
again.
[laughter]
Yeah.
Like very difficult, you know.
Yeah. Super entertaining. But
Oh, super entertaining.
But people could have the impression now
when they see Chris jack up for a mass
like why didn't he make it?
Yes. Yes.
I've said I've said that in commentary
um that um we as viewers sometimes we
put too much pressure on these players
because we expect so much you know.
Yeah. And um I even I even get comments
on my YouTube channel when I have
champions playing
that uh are not very becoming of the
players. You know, they say, "Oh, these
guys are terrible or whatever." You
don't you don't know. You know, you
obviously don't watch matches in their
entirety because that's just the way
pool is sometimes, right?
Yeah. You have to realize that people
also have to climb into a match
sometimes and they have to grow into a
match.
It's true.
And uh the danger nowadays is oh he's
not he's not running out right five
racks right out of the gate. Zap next
match.
Right. Exactly.
That's you know when we were buying the
Acustat VHS that period we were watching
one video 10 times.
Yeah. And you could watch it and you
could watch it from an an offensive
angle, defensive angle, the one player
struggling getting back in the game. You
could, you know, you the position play,
the tactical side. You could learn ton
of things out of one match. But I I feel
the danger now sometimes is the
entertainment factor because there's so
much out there. It's like next next
and you have to Yeah. You have to
understand that
that's not really how these players
become great players. They also
struggle,
right?
Yeah.
So,
well, thank you for your time today. I I
I do have one more question. Uh, you
know, for those who don't know you, you
are a competitive player. uh you you've
you know like I said you know your
resume is is is extensive in
professional pool. What about action
matches? I I know I've never really
heard of you to get into
a $10,000 head-to-head match or a some
type of a gambling scenario. Did you
walk away from that?
Uh
was that a decision you made? A
conscious decision? I was early 20s. I
was gambling a lot when I when I was
touring the US. You know, I I think I
visited almost half the states in the
country uh between my 20th and 23rd.
Okay.
And then I chose to become a
professional
uh and the professional side of the
sport is more the tournament scene. You
can get sponsors through the tournament
scene. You can get invitations to bigger
tournaments, invitational tournaments,
etc. So uh if you want to play the sport
in that sense as an athlete you have to
go tournaments but
uh I do miss the action because it gives
you an opportunity to play your aame
longer or play the game longer. What I
sometimes don't like about tournaments
is you play one match a day
and you have to go back to the hotel
room. So you're like you finally feel
you warmed up and the match is over. And
we all started playing pool to play pool
and not to play one match a day, right?
We want to play. So that's what I do
miss. Uh
yeah, I I do miss the longer sets, but
uh I have a young family and it's
sometimes just hard to combine because
if you have a big match, you have to fly
in, jet lag, uh acclam,
what do you say?
Acclimate. Yeah,
acclimate. So it's like boom, another
week and I'm already gone uh five months
out of the year, six months out of the
year with tournaments.
I see. I see. So at the moment it's a
little bit tougher. Um
I mean I I sorry to interrupt you but I
I have to say I mean I'm I'm
sure that you've been approached right
someone says hey I'll back you in a
match you know you haven't got but
you've declined. Is that correct?
No there was only one or two uh
times where it came close. Uh, we were
Yeah, I don't know if you should say
it's it's no big deal. We were I was
You don't need names. You just
No, I was almost going to play uh one or
two Americans, [snorts]
but then at the end it had to be in
their room.
And uh the backer that uh um that I
spoke with, he said, "Yeah, I don't
really want to go there." And so it kind
of fell apart because I was almost going
to fly in and play that match. Wow.
It was getting really close.
So, yeah, potentially in the future I
still uh I wouldn't mind playing a few
games because I I I do enjoy it.
Yeah.
But, uh as of now, it's it's a little
bit tough to combine.
I would imagine too that uh you know,
from the perspective of your your course
as well that it's a different side of
the mental game, right? Because the
difference between being in a tournament
and between between being in an action
match uh you know there are many aspects
of that g that competition that are so
different you know like playing much
longer sessions
um having to deal with your opponent on
a long-term basis.
Yeah, true. It's the opponent comes more
into play, right? uh you're not only
playing the game then because uh you
have to start thinking about his
strength strengths or weaknesses on push
outs stuff like that and uh stamina is a
big thing fatigue right uh
equipment
uh is maybe different pressure
but I think uh I heard Alex Balion say
this once in an interview with a bunch
of players we were all there in
Philippines and I agreed on this he that
uh the action matches complement the
tournament player and the tournament
matches complement the action player.
You both pick up things that you can put
in the other
side of the spectrum.
Yeah. Like a tool like a tool bag
like a tool like for uh tournament
players are used to finishing the
matches more where an action player
[snorts]
if he loses the set he's just all right
let's flip it again.
Flip the coin. Yeah.
So, the pressure of finishing is
different
unless it's really a huge set.
So, for an action player, you see a lot
that they're used to the freewheeling,
fast, boom, loose, and they have a
harder time with with the grinding part
of the tournament.
And the tournament player is used to
more percentage play and he has a harder
time maybe to let let go to to just to
just rip it, right? to actually save
energy by letting his whole game just
explode because he has plenty of time to
adjust.
So it I think that is an interesting uh
psychological factor like both both
sides can complement each other.
Yeah, that's a very good that's good
insight from Alex Pagalion.
Um well great nails, I really appreciate
your time with us. Um uh you also have
uh you know I just want to tell the
viewers out there I want to recommend
that they go to uh your website and uh
and and and and look at the course. You
also have a free uh a free part of the
course as well like masterful
uh isn't there a masterful goal setting?
Yeah.
Now that's that's the a free course that
they can take right now. Is that
correct?
Correct. the the master for goal setting
is uh six videos. It's six steps of how
to make a goal setting schedule for
yourself. Very powerful stuff
and I I wanted to give that as a freebie
to all the pool players and also to try
my skills in that department, the
production side and see how things were
working. I was I was very satisfied. And
then I took it a step further with the
full course and that's of course a
totally different level. and uh you get
this the 30 minute Skype oneonone.
There's there's way more extra content,
33 videos. So uh it's very complete and
of course from 25 years of experience.
So uh that's that's the next step.
Yeah. Well, great. So from every skill
level, please check out the free
masterful goal setting for competitive
players curriculum. And when you're
ready to take your mental game to the
next level, enroll in the mental edge
for competitive pool players. Go to
terminator-col.com.
I'm speaking with Neil's uh Fen, the uh
uh the uh the brains and the broad
behind the idea.
[laughter]
Um and I want to thank you for being a
guest on POV pool, Neils. Um is there
anything anything that you can leave us
with?
No, I just want to say uh you know it's
different parts of the world it's it's
different emotions right now. Uh some
people very frustrated and sad maybe
family has been hit by the corona.
Some people are getting very edgy they
can't play. I think we all try and be
patient and you know stay safe and if
you can I just really advise you to go
outside. I also see a lot of people
they're getting slightly depressed
because they're staying indoors so much
and it's just gonna it's just going to
drive you crazy. Just go outside, enjoy
the springtime.
Yeah.
Get air, get light, maybe, you know,
start working out.
Yeah.
Uh to also blow off some steam, right?
Some frustration and getting locked up.
Start start running, start biking. I
think that's walking. I think that's
that's very positive things for your uh
well-being. So,
especially especially pool players who
can't play pool because, you know, like
my friend Chris Schwart, he owns
California Billiards. He said, you know,
we're pool players. We just want to get
out there and and about the
equipment and, you know, like, you know,
talk about talk about the matches that
we could have won or, you know,
whatever. We just want to get out there
and and and and talk, you know, like
we're pool players and that's how we
are.
It's like lock caged up uh tigers,
right?
I know. It's it's uh it's frustrating
for me, too. This was a difficult uh you
know, I've shared this before on my
podcast. You know, I've I had a
difficult uh process of acceptance of
this whole situation.
Yeah.
So, um uh so I think I'm you know, I
hope I'm overcoming it. But uh once
again, Neils, thank you so much for
spending time with us. Uh uh also uh
Neils has a Facebook page, Neils Fen
official on Facebook. And u you know,
once again,
Neil Terminator F official.
What's that?
Neil's the Terminator F.
Oh, okay. Neil's Neil's the Terminator
Fine. Because there's another Oh, yeah.
That Yes, that's true. The title of your
of your Facebook. That's true. Neil's
the Terminator Fine. And um and once
again that is um uh terminator-col.com
for uh the uh for the Terminator College
course. So thanks a lot again, Neils.
Thank you guys. All right. Thanks,
Daniel.
You're welcome. Thank you.